<Variables>

	<Property bean="session" name="id" property="id">
        <Description>Contains the session id of the current session</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
VARIABLE
   id - The session id of the current session.

DESCRIPTION
   The read-only ${id} variable contains the session id of the current
   session and primarily useful for including in the prompt.
   
SEE ALSO
   prompt, \sessions
        ]]></Help>	
	</Property>
	
	
	<Property bean="session" name="connected" property="connected">
        <Description>Indicates whether or not the current session is connected</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
VARIABLE
   connected - Indicates whether or not the current session is connected

DESCRIPTION
   The read-only ${connected} variable will contain the value "true" if
   the current session is connected to a server, otherwise "false". This
   is primarily useful for including in the prompt.
   
SEE ALSO
   prompt, \connect
        ]]></Help>	
	</Property>
	
	
	<Property bean="session" name="rc" property="lastCommandResult"/>
	<Property bean="session" name="IFS" property="stringExpander.IFS"/>
	
	<Property bean="session" name="database" property="connection.catalog" 
	          settable="true" quiet="true">
        <Description>Contains the connection's current database</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
VARIABLE
   database - Contains the connection's current database

DESCRIPTION
   The ${database} variable will contain the name of the database
   (or 'catalog' in JDBC terminology) of the current session if it connected
   to a server. In addition, the database context of the current connection
   can be changed by setting the ${database} variable to the desired 
   database name.
   
SEE ALSO
   \connect, dflt_database
        ]]></Help>	
	</Property>
	
	
	<Property bean="session" name="autocommit" property="connection.autoCommit" 
	          settable="true" quiet="false">
        <Description>Contains the connection's current auto-commit status</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
VARIABLE
   autocommit - Contains the connection's current auto-commit status

DESCRIPTION
   The ${autocommit} variable indicates whether or not the current connection
   is in auto-commit mode. In addition, the connections autocommit mode can be 
   altered by setting this variable.  To change the autocommit mode for
   all future connections, use the ${dflt_autocommit} variable.
   
SEE ALSO
   \connect, dflt_autocommit
        ]]></Help>	
	</Property>
	          
	<Property bean="session" name="interactive" property="interactive">
        <Description>Whether or not the current session is interactive</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
VARIABLE
   interactive - Indicates whether or not the current session is interactive

DESCRIPTION
   The read-only ${interactive} variable will contain "true" if the current
   session is interactive, or "false" otherwise.
        ]]></Help>	
	</Property>
	
	<Property bean="session" name="domain" property="SQLContext.domain"
	          quiet="true">
        <Description>Windows domain used to establish connection</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
VARIABLE
   domain - Windows domain used to establish the database connection

DESCRIPTION
   The read-only ${domain} variable will contain the name of the Windows
   domain used to authenticate the database connection. This property is
   defined locally to the session and is only available if domain 
   authentication was used then creating the connection.
   
SEE ALSO
   user, driver, server, port
        ]]></Help>	
	</Property>
	
	<Property bean="session" name="user" property="SQLContext.username"
	          quiet="true">
        <Description>Username used to establish database connection</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
VARIABLE
   user - The username used when connection was established.

DESCRIPTION
   The read-only ${user} variable will contain the username used
   to authenticate the database connection. This property is
   defined locally to the session and is only available when a connection
   has been established.
   
SEE ALSO
   domain, driver, server, port
        ]]></Help>	
	</Property>
	
	<Property bean="session" name="server" property="SQLContext.server"
	          quiet="true">
        <Description>Database server name connected to</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
VARIABLE
   server - The server that the connection is currently established.

DESCRIPTION
   The read-only ${server} variable will contain the name of the server
   to which the current session has a connection established. If no
   connection is established then this variable will not be set.
   
SEE ALSO
   domain, driver, user, port
        ]]></Help>	
	</Property>
	
	<Property bean="session" name="port" property="SQLContext.port"
	          quiet="true">
        <Description>TCP port used to establish database connection</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
VARIABLE
   port - The TCP port to which the database connection is established.

DESCRIPTION
   The read-only ${port} variable will contain the TCP port used
   to establish the database connection. This property is
   defined locally to the session and is only available when a connection
   has been established.
   
SEE ALSO
   domain, driver, server, user
        ]]></Help>	
	</Property>
	
	<Property bean="session" name="server" property="SQLContext.server"
	          quiet="true">
        <Description>Database server name connected to</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
VARIABLE
   server - The server that the connection is currently established.

DESCRIPTION
   The read-only ${server} variable will contain the name of the server
   to which the current session has a connection established. If no
   connection is established then this variable will not be set.
   
SEE ALSO
   domain, driver, user, port
        ]]></Help>	
	</Property>
	
	<Property bean="session" name="SID" property="SQLContext.sid"
	          quiet="true">
        <Description>Oracle instance to which connection is established</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
VARIABLE
   SID - Oracle instance name to which a connection is established.

DESCRIPTION
   The read-only ${SID} variable will contain the name of the Oracle
   instance to which the current session has a connection established. If no
   connection is established (or the connection isn't to Oracle) then this
   variable will not be set.
   
SEE ALSO
   domain, driver, user, server, port
        ]]></Help>	
	</Property>
	
	<Property bean="session" name="jdbc_url" property="SQLContext.url"
	          quiet="true">
        <Description>The JDBC URL that was used for connection</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
VARIABLE
   jdbc_url - The JDBC URL that was used to establish the current connection

DESCRIPTION
   The read-only ${jdbc_url} variable will contain the name of the JDBC
   URL that was used to establish the current database connection. If no
   connection is established then this variable will not be set.
   
SEE ALSO
   domain, driver, user, server, port, SID
        ]]></Help>	
	</Property>
	
	<Property bean="session" name="driver" property="SQLContext.driver"
	          quiet="true">
        <Description>The JSqsh driver used to establish connection</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
VARIABLE
   driver - The JSqsh driver name that was used when establishing a connection

DESCRIPTION
   The read-only ${driver} variable will contain the name of the JSqsh
   driver that was used to establish the current database connection. If no
   connection is established then this variable will not be set.
   
SEE ALSO
   domain, driver, user, server, port, SID
        ]]></Help>	
	</Property>
	
	<Property bean="session" name="name" property="SQLContext.logicalName"
	          quiet="true">
        <Description>The logical name used for the current connection</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
VARIABLE
   name - The logical name used for the current connection.

DESCRIPTION
   The read-only ${name} variable reflects the logical name that was 
   associated with the current database connection of the connection
   was established with the --name argument. If there is no logical 
   connection name or no database connection is currently established,
   then this will have a null value.
   
SEE ALSO
   domain, driver, user, server, port, SID
        ]]></Help>	
	</Property>
	
</Variables>