<Variables>
	<Dynamic class="org.sqsh.variables.DimensionVariable"  
	         name="window_size" value="600x400">
        <Description>Size of the window opened in graphical mode</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `window_size` - Size of window opened in graphical mode.

## Description

  The `${window_size}` variable defines the width and height of the window
  opened when jsqsh is asked to display in graphical mode. The default
  value is 600x400.
   
## SEE ALSO

[[style]]
        ]]></Help>
    </Dynamic> 
    
	<Dynamic class="org.sqsh.variables.FontVariable"  
	         name="font" value="Monospaced-10">
        <Description>Font used for gui displays</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `font` - Font to be used for GUI displays.

## Description

  The `${font}` variable specifies the name of the font that will be
  used when jsqsh opens a graphical output window. This occurs either
  when the `-g` parameter is passed to a command (e.g. `\go -g`) or 
  when the display mode is set to `graphical`.
   
  The font specification is of the form:
   
    Fontname-size
       
  With the default being:
   
    Monospaced-10
       
## See also

  [[style]], [[options]]
        ]]></Help>
    </Dynamic> 
	         
	<String name="prompt" value="#if($connected==true)[$server][$user] #end$lineno>">
        <Description>Defines the query prompt</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `prompt` - Defines the query prompt.

## Description

  The `${prompt}` variable defines the prompt that will be displayed before
  each line of input. Unlike other variables, this variable may, itself,
  contain variables that will be expanded prior to display.
   
  For example, the default value:
   
    #if($connected==true)[$server][$user] #end$lineno>
      
  will show:
   
    1>
      
  when not connected to a server and:
   
    [prod-db][sa] 1> 
      
  when connected (the `#if`/`#end` syntax is part of Velocity, the tool
  that is used to expand variables. Documentation is available from
  http://velocity.apache.org/engine/releases/velocity-1.5/user-guide.html).
   
  Care must be taken when setting this variable to ensure that the
  varables are not expanded when it is being set. For example:
   
    1> \set prompt="$lineno>"
      
  will have the $lineno expanded at the time the prompt is set and
  is exactly identical to:
   
    1> \set prompt="1>"
      
  which clearly isn't what you inteded. Instead use single quotes:
   
    1> \set prompt='$lineno>'
   
## See also

  [[\set]]
        ]]></Help>
	</String>
	
	<Property bean="global" name="terminator" property="terminatorString">
        <Description>Defines the SQL statement terminator</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `terminator` - Defines the SQL statement terminator.

## Description

  The `${terminator}` variable defines a single character that can be used
  to terminate a SQL statement or block and cause it to be executed without
  having to issue a `\go`, for example:
   
    1> select * from sysobjects;
       
  will directly execute the query because `;` is the current terminator.
   
  `\unset`'ing this variable disables the in-line query terminator feature
  and requires that you explicitly issue a `\go` to execute your queries.
   
  Be very careful choosing an alternative terminator, since you don't
  want to be inadvertently executing queries.

## Command terminator

  As of jsqsh 1.5, the terminator may also be used to terminate a line
  with a jsqsh command. For example, if `;` is the current terminator
  then you can type:
   
    1> \echo hello how are you;
    hello how are you
   
  and the terminator will be silently ignored. If any input follows 
  the terminator, an error will be issued:
   
    1> \echo hello; there
    Input is not allowed after the command terminator `;`
   
## See also

  [[\go]], [[\unset]]
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>
    
	<Property bean="global" name="editing_mode" property="console.editingMode">
        <Description>Controls the editing mode for the line editor</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[

## Variable

  `editing_mode` - Controls the editing mode for the line editor.

## Description

  The `${editing_mode}` variable can be used to set or display the editing
  mode of the underlying line editing implementing, for example to switch
  to `emacs` or `vi` key sets.  Currently only the JLine editor supports
  this feature, all others will display this variable as null and will
  error when attempting to set this variable.
   
  JLine supports the following modes:
   
  * `vi` - The vi key set, starting out in insertion mode
  * `vi-insert` - The vi key set, starting out in insertion mode
  * `vi-move` - The vi key set, starting out in move/command mode
  * `emacs` - The emacs key set, starting out in insertion mode
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>
    
	<Property bean="version" name="version" property="version" settable="false">
        <Description>The jsqsh version number</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[

## Variable

  `version` - Contains the jsqsh version number

## Description

  The `${version}` variable contains the jsqsh version number. This variable
  is not set-able.
   
## See also

  [[build_date]]
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>
    
	<Property bean="version" name="build_date" property="buildDate" settable="false">
        <Description>The jsqsh build date</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `build_date` - Contains the jsqsh build date

## Description

  The `${build_date}` variable contains the date at which the version of jsqsh
  was compiled.
   
## See also

  [[build_date]]
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>
	
	<!-- Property values are referring to properties of the session -->
	<Property bean="global" name="lineno" property="bufferManager.current.lineNumber">
        <Description>Contains the current line number being entered</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `lineno` - Contains the current line number being entered

## Description

  The `${lineno}` variable contains the current line number being entered
  into the current SQL buffer. This variable cannot be set directly. To
  clear the current buffer (and thus revert to line 1) utilize the `\reset`
  command.
   
## See also

  [[\reset]]
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>
	
	<Property bean="global" name="width" property="screenWidth">
        <Description>The screen display width</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `width` - The screen display width

## Description

  The `${width}` variable controls the width of the screen that jsqsh uses
  when formatting output. By default, this variable is derived by directly
  polling your terminal and, thus, the value can change if your terminal
  is resized, however setting the variable to an explicit value fixes the
  display width to the size requested.  Setting the variable to a value
  less than zero, causes the width of the terminal to be utilized again.
   
## See also

  [[style]]
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>
	
	
	<Property bean="global" name="histsize" property="bufferManager.maxBuffers">
		<Description>Controls the number of SQL statements retained in history</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `histsize` - Controls the number of SQL statements retained in history

## Description

  The `${histsize}` variable determines the number of SQL statements
  that is retained historically (the default is 50). Each time a 
  SQL statement is executed with the `\go` command, that statement
  is saved away and be re-edited and re-executed later if desired.
   
  The `\history` command shows the last `${histsize}` SQL statements
  executed and `\buf-edit` can be used to edit and re-run a 
  previously executed statement. Also, see **[[buffers]]** for
  details on how to refer to specific buffers.
   
## See also

  [[buffers]], [[\history]]
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>
    
	<Property bean="global" name="histid" property="bufferManager.current.id">
		<Description>The history id of the current buffer</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `histid` - The history id of the current buffer

## Description

  The read-only `${histid}` variable can be used to retrieve the history
  id of the current buffer.  That is, the number under which the current
  buffer will appear from `\history` after it is executed. This is particularly
  useful within the `${prompt}` variable. 
   
## See also

  [[buffers]], [[prompt]], [[\history]]
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>
	
	<Property bean="global" name="readline" property="console.name">
		<Description>Displays the readline implementation in use</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `readline` - Displays the readline implementation in use.

## Description

  The read-only `${readline}` variable displays the mechanism that is
  being used to read input. 
   
  JSqsh is written in Java and java provides no easy mechanism to 
  work with the console for activities such as editing the current 
  line, or scrolling forward and backward through history or performing
  command-line completion.  As a result, JSqsh relies upon some 3rd
  party libraries to assist in these activities, some of which are
  actual native code rather than Java code. 
   
  Upon start up, JSqsh goes through some logic to determine which
  libraries are available on your platform and it chooses the first
  available that it can successfully utilize in the following order:
   
  * `jline` - JLine is an almost-pure java API that provides much of the 
    functionality of GNU readline. It is the default editor for jsqsh.
    Documentation is available at:  
    https://github.com/jline/jline2
  * `readline` - This is an interface to the GNU readline API. This
    library provides full command line editing and completion
    plus has configurable key-bindings and modes for those 
    that prefer different configurations. Documentation
    for configuring is available from:  
    http://tiswww.case.edu/php/chet/readline/rltop.html
  * `editline` - This is an interface to the NetBSD editline library. This 
    library is very similar in functionality to GNU Readline. Documentation 
    for configuring is available from:  
    http://linux.die.net/man/5/editrc
  * `getline` - Getline is used primarily on Windows and provides basic 
    command line editing, but no completion functionality.
  * `purejava` - This is the most basic interface and provides no editing 
    or completion functionality.
   
Although it is not possible to change the readline library at run-time,
  you may force the library to be used with with the `--readline` command
  line option to jsqsh or by setting the `JSQSH_READLINE` environment variable.
  Both methods may be provided one of the names above.
              
## See also

  [[options]]
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>
	
	
	<Property bean="global" name="scale" property="dataFormatter.scale">
		<Description>Controls the decimal place precision of values</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `scale` - Controls digits displayed after decimal for floating point values

## Description

  When display floating point values, `${scale}` determines how many of the
  total `${precision}` digits are used to represent values following the
  decimal place.  For example:
   
    Actual Value  Precision Scale      Displayed Value
    ------------  --------- ---------- ---------------
       1.2345678          5          2            1.23
       1.2345678          5          3           1.234
       1.2345678          5          4          1.2345
           
  This property only applies to types of real, float, double and Oracle 
  NUMERIC (with no precision or scale specified).

## See also

  [[precision]]
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>
	
	<Property bean="global" name="precision" property="dataFormatter.precision">
		<Description>Controls the decimal place precision of values</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `precision` - Controls number of digits displayed in floating point values

## Description

  When display floating point values, `${precision}` determines how many
  total digits of the value are displayed. `${scale}` is used in conjunction
  with this value to indicate how many of those digits are used to show
  the values after the decimal.
   
  This property only applies to types of real, float, double and
  Oracle NUMERIC (with no precision or scale specified).

## See also

  `scale`
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>

	<Property bean="global" name="binstr_fmt" 
                  property="dataFormatter.byteStringFormat">
		<Description>Changes the manner in which binary values are displayed</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `binstr_fmt` - Controls the manner in which binary values are displayed

## Description

  This is a boolean (`true`/`false`) value that controls the manner in which 
  jsqsh displays binary values.  The default (`false`) causes jsqsh to
  display binary values as pure hex values, such as:

    0xabcd

  changing this value to true, causes jsqsh to display the values in hex
  string format, such as:

    X'abcd'
     
## See also

  [[fmt_date]], [[precision]], [[scale]]
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>
	
	<Property bean="global" name="fmt_date" property="dataFormatter.dateFormat">
		<Description>Controls the representation of date</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `fmt_date` - Controls the representation of date values.

## Description

  The `${fmt_date}` variable contains a format string that is utilized
  when display columns of type DATE. The format string follows java
  SimpleDateFormat conventions, which are documented here:
   
  https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/text/SimpleDateFormat.html
      
  The default is `MMM dd yyyy`.
   
## See also

  [[fmt_datetime]], [[fmt_time]]
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>

	<Property bean="global" name="fmt_time" property="dataFormatter.timeFormat">
		<Description>Controls the representation of time</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `fmt_time` - Controls the representation of time values.

## Description

  The `${fmt_time}` variable contains a format string that is utilized
  when display columns of type TIME. The format string follows java
  SimpleDateFormat conventions, which are documented here:
   
  https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/text/SimpleDateFormat.html
      
  The default is `HH:mm`.
   
## See also

  [[fmt_datetime]], [[fmt_time]]
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>
	
	<Property bean="global" name="fmt_datetime" property="dataFormatter.datetimeFormat">
		<Description>Controls the representation of datatimes</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `fmt_datetime` - Controls the representation of datatime values.

## Description
  The `${fmt_datetime}` variable contains a format string that is utilized
  when display columns of type DATETIME. The format string follows java
  SimpleDateFormat conventions, which are documented here:
   
  https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/text/SimpleDateFormat.html
      
  The default is `MMM dd yyyy HH:mm:ss`.
   
## See also

  [[fmt_date]], [[fmt_time]]
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>
	
	<Property bean="global" name="null" property="dataFormatter.null">
		<Description>Controls the representation of nulls</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `null` - Controls the visual representation of nulls

## Description

  The `${null}` variable is used when displaying null values. The default
  value is "[NULL]", which will be shown whenever a null value is 
  encountered.
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>
	
	<Property bean="global" name="maxlen" property="rendererManager.maxColumnWidth">
		<Description>The maximum display width of a column</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `maxlen` - The maximum display width of a column

## Description

  The `${maxlen}` variable determines the maximum width that any individual
  column may consume (the default is 35). Columns exceeding that width 
  will have their contents word-wrapped, if necessary, during display. This
  variable may not be utilized in all display styles (e.g. it is ignored
  by the `perfect` style).
   
## See also

  `style`
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>
	
	<Property bean="global" name="nocount" property="SQLRenderer.noCount">
		<Description>Controls display of "rows affected" from update/deletes</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `nocount` - Controls the display of "rows affected" due to updates and deletes

## Description

  The `${nocount}` variable can be used to suppress the output of:
   
    (XXX rows affected)
      
  that are generated by INSERT, UPDATE, and DELETE statements (that is,
  statements that do not generate row results). 
   
  Note that some platforms allow these sorts of counts to be disabled at
  the server (e.g. Sybase's and Microsoft's `set nocount on` option). 
  This variable does NOT turn the setting off at the server, but simply
  hides the messages from display.
   
  The default value is `false`, indicating that these results should be
  displayed.
   
## See also

  [[\go]]
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>
	
	<Property bean="global" name="querytime" property="SQLRenderer.showTimings">
		<Description>Controls display of query timing information</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `querytime` - Controls the display of query execution time information

## Description

  The `${querytime}` variable can be used to display or suppress the
  output of query execution time information. The timing information
  displayed is the execution as seen by jsqsh (which includes network
  time), not necessarily the time spent in the server.
   
## See also

  [[nocount]]
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>
	
	<Property bean="global" name="maxrows" property="SQLRenderer.maxRows">
		<Description>Limits the size of query results</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `maxrows` - Limits the size of query results.

## Description

  The `${maxrows}` variable can be used to limit the number of rows returned
  by any individual query in a batch of SQL (the default is 500). A value
  of zero or less indicates that query result sizes should be unlimited.
   
  For certain display styles (see [[style]]), query results are retained
  entirely in memory so it is important the results not be unbounded.
   
## See also

  [[style]]
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>
	
	<Property bean="global" name="maxrows_method" 
	          property="SQLRenderer.rowLimitMethodName">
		<Description>Controls method used to limit rows</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `maxrows_method` - Controls the mechanism used to limit result set rows

## Description

  The `${maxrows_method}` variable is used to control the mechanism that is
  used to limit result rows as specified by the `${maxrows}` variable. This
  variable may be one of the following:
   
  * `discard` (default)  
    This causes jsqsh to silently discard all rows beyond 
   `${maxrows}`. This is the safest and recommended mechanism to utilize 
   but can cause delays as additional network traffic as the rows are processed.
     
  * `cancel`  
    This causes jsqsh to issue a cancel to stop the processing of the query 
    when `${maxrows}` is reached. This can cause side effects because it cancels 
    the entire query, not just the current result set. For example, if you 
    were calling a stored procedure or a SQL batch that contained multiple 
    statements or queries, the cancel would stop the processing at the first 
    query that returned more than `${maxrows}`.
    
  * `driver`  
    This causes jsqsh to ask the JDBC driver to limit row results to 
    `${maxrows}` (via the drivers `Statement.setMaxRows()` method). This method 
    has been shown to have side effects in some drivers of not just limiting 
    the result rows but also limiting UPDATEs and DELETEs to `${maxrows}`.
               
## See also

  [[maxrows]]
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>
	
	
	
	<Property bean="global" name="expand" property="SQLRenderer.expand">
		<Description>Determines if SQL will have variable expansion performed</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `expand` - Determines if SQL will have variable expansion performed

## Description

  The `${expand}` variable is a boolean, accepting either `false` (the default)
  or `true`. The value of this variable will be used to determine if sqsh
  will attempt to expand SQL statements being executed of any sqsh variables
  they may contain before execution.
  
  The `expand` variable is `false` by default for safety. JSqsh doesn't know
  the dialect of SQL of that target database and it is possible that `$foo` may
  be a valid expression or identifier and variable expansion could cause 
  unwanted side effects and possible data loss.
  
## See also

  [[\go]]
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>
	
	<Property bean="global" name="show_meta" property="SQLRenderer.showMetadata">
		<Description>Controls display of result set descriptions</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `show_meta` - Controls the display of result set metadata.

## Description
  The `${show_meta}` variable causes result set metadata (column names, 
  data types, etc.) to be displayed as a separate result set just before
  the actual row results. This feature is primarily intended as a debugging
  tool for jsqsh development and/or developers that want to diagnose 
  issues with result handling in their applications.
   
## See also
  [[\go]]
        ]]></Help>
	</Property>
	
	
	<Property bean="global" name="shell" property="shellManager.shellCommand">
		<Description>Defines the O/S shell used to execute commands</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `shell` - Defines the O/S shell that is used to execute commands

## Description

  The `${shell}` variable defines the external operating system program (shell)
  that will be used when executing external commands. This variable is
  used when:
   
  * Executing a pipe (e.g. **go | more**)
  * Utilizing a back-tick (e.g. **\echo \`echo hi\`**)
  * Running external editors (e.g. by **\buf-edit**).
   
The variable must contain the name of the shell, plus a comma-delimited
  list of arguments to pass to the shell. A special argument of `?` must
  be provided to indicate where the command being executed should be 
  placed.
   
  On UNIX platforms, `${shell}` will be defaulted to:
   
    /bin/sh,-c,?
       
  which means, for example, when running `go | more`, the `more` command
  will be launched via:
   
    /bin/sh -c "more"
      
  On Windows platforms `${shell}` will be defaulted to:
   
    cmd.exe,/c,?
      
## See also

  [[\buf-edit|\buf_edit]]
        ]]></Help>
	
	</Property>
	
	
	
	<Property bean="global" name="dflt_database" property="driverManager.defaultDatabase">
		<Description>Controls the default database for new connections</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `dflt_database` - Controls the default database for new connections

## Description

  The `dflt_database` variable can be used to place new connections in 
  a specific database (or catalog, in JDBC terminology).
   
## See also

  [[database]]
        ]]></Help>
    </Property>
    
	<Property bean="global" name="dflt_username" property="driverManager.defaultUsername">
		<Description>Controls the default username for new connections</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `dflt_username` - Controls the default username for new connections

## Description

  The `${dflt_username}` variable specifies the username to use for all 
  connections if the username is not explicitly provided.
   
## See also

  [[dflt_driver]], [[dflt_database]]
        ]]></Help>
    </Property>
    
	<Property bean="global" name="dflt_driver" property="driverManager.defaultDriver">
		<Description>Controls the default JDBC driver name for new connections</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `dflt_driver` - Controls the default JDBC driver name for new connections

## Description

  The `${dflt_driver}` specifies the logical JDBC driver name to be used for 
  connections when no driver name is explicitly provided
   
## See also

  [[dflt_driver]], [[dflt_username]], [[dflt_database]], [[\drivers]]
        ]]></Help>
    </Property>
	
	<Property bean="global" name="dflt_autocommit" property="driverManager.defaultAutoCommit">
		<Description>Controls the autocommit setting for new connections</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable
  [[dflt_autocommit]] - Controls the autocommit setting for new connections

## Description

  The `${dflt_autocommit}` variables controls the SQL auto-commit setting 
  that will be set for all new connections that are created.  Auto-commit
  refers to the transaction mode that a connection uses; when auto-commit
  is true, then each statement issued is executed as if it was in its
  own transaction (that is, as if the user typed 'commit' after executing
  the statement.  When auto-commit is false, then the connection stays
  in an open transaction until you explicitly issue a commit to the database.
   
## See also

  [[autocommit]]
        ]]></Help>
    </Property>
	
    <Property bean="global" name="classpath"
              property="driverManager.classpath">
        <Description>Defines JDBC driver locations</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `classpath` - Defines additional JDBC driver search locations
   
## Description

  The `${classpath}` variable can be used to specify places in which 
  JDBC drivers can be found on your system. The path is specified
  as a delimited list of ".jar" files or directories containing ".jar"
  files.  The delimiter is `;` on Windows or `:` on UNIX.  The following
  is an example of a valid UNIX classpath:
   
    /home/gray/jars/sybase.jar:/home/gray/drivers/
      
  where the first entry is an explicitly specified jar file (`sybase.jar`)
  and the second entry is the path to a directory that contains multiple
  jars, each of which will become part of the classpath.
   
## See also

  [[\drivers]]
        ]]></Help>
    </Property>
    
    <Property bean="global" name="headers"
              property="rendererManager.showHeaders">
        <Description>Controls column header display</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `headers` - Controls the display of column headers
   
## Description

  The `${headers}` variable can be used to turn on or off the display of
  column header information in query results.  The default value is `true`.
   
## See also

  [[footers]]
        ]]></Help>
    </Property>
    
    <Property bean="global" name="footers"
              property="rendererManager.showFooters">
        <Description>Controls query footer information</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `footers` - Controls the display of query footer information
   
## Description

  The `${footers}` variable can be used to turn on or off the display of
  query footer information in query results. Footer information includes
  the row count, update count, and query timing that is normally displayed
  after each result set is displayed. The default value is `true`.
   
## See also

  `headers`
        ]]></Help>
    </Property>
    
    <Property bean="global" name="echo" property="inputEchoed">
        <Description>Echo all input</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `echo` - Controls echoing of input to stdout 
   
## Description
  If set to `true` the `${echo}` variable causes every line that is read
  as input to be echoed back out to output. The typical use of this is
  when running jsqsh non-interactively with a script. With this option on,
  you will see all of the SQL and commands as well as the output of all of
  the commands.
        ]]></Help>
    </Property>
    
    <Property bean="global" name="perfect_sample_rows"
              property="rendererManager.perfectSampleSize">
        <Description>Determines number of rows sampled by "perfect" renderers</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `perfect_sample_rows` - Controls the display of query footer information
   
## Description

  The `${perfect_sample_rows}` determines the number of rows that are 
  sampled (held in memory) by perfect result renderers (such as used 
  by the "perfect" display style) before results are displayed.  The
  larger this number, the better the results will be rendered, however
  the more memory will be consumed as all the rows must be held in memory
  before display.
   
  A value less than 1 indicates that all rows will be sampled prior to
  display.  The default value is 500.
   
## See also

  [[style]]
        ]]></Help>
    </Property>
    
  	<Property bean="global" name="show_stack" property="printStackTrace">
        <Description>Enables/disables display of stack trace from exceptions</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `show_stack` - Controls whether or not stack traces are display from exceptions

## Description

  Note: this variable has been depricated. You should use `${ex_detail}` now
  to control the level of detail in exceptions.
   
  The `${show_stack}` boolean variable controls whether or not exceptions
  thrown during the execution of a command (such as `\go`) will display
  just the text of the exception or the full stack trace.  The default 
  is `false`, limiting the output to just the text of the exception.
  This is typically only set to true if you need to debug a problem within
  a driver or possibly a specific command.
   
  Currently not all places that deal with exceptions in jsqsh honor this
  setting.
   
## See also
  show_exclass
        ]]></Help>	
	</Property>
    
	<Property bean="global" name="show_exclass" property="printExceptionClass">
        <Description>Enables/disables display of exceptions class name</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `show_exclass` - Controls whether or not the exception class name is displayed

## Description

  The `${show_exclass}` boolean variable controls whether or not exceptions
  thrown during the execution of a command (such as `\go`) will display
  the class name of the exception, along with the text of the exception. The
  default is `false`. This is typically only set to true if you need to 
  debug a problem within a driver or possibly a specific command.
   
  Currently not all places that deal with exceptions in jsqsh honor this
  setting.
   
## See also

  [[show_stack]]
        ]]></Help>	
	</Property>
	
  	<Property bean="global" name="ex_detail" property="exceptionDetailString">
        <Description>Sets the level of detail when displaying exceptions</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `ex_detail` - Controls the level of detail when displaying exceptions

## Description
  The `${ex_detail}` variable can be used to control the amount of information
  produced by exceptions.  The available levels are:
   
  * `low` - Displays just the exception class name and, for SQL exceptions, 
    the SQL code and state.
  * `medium` - (default) Displays the SQL code and state (for SQL exceptions) 
    the text of the exception, and the same information for any nested 
    exceptions.
  * `high` - Displays everything from medium, plus the stack trace for each.
   
## See also

  [[show_exclass]]
        ]]></Help>	
	</Property>
	
  	<Property bean="global" name="timeout" property="queryTimeout">
        <Description>Sets the number of seconds before queries time out</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `timeout` - Controls the number of seconds before a query is timed out

## Description

  The `${timeout}` variable is used to control the number of seconds before a
  query is timed out.  When the variable is set from the sqshrc file or from
  a session that has not yet established a connection, it defines the default
  timeout for all connections. When set from the context of an already
  established connection, it controls only the timeout for queries on that
  connection.
   
  If a JDBC connection is established, and the driver supports query timeouts,
  then the JDBC driver is asked to time the queries out (the behavior of which
  is dependant upon the driver vendor).  If the connection does not support
  query timeouts, then jsqsh will automatically cancel the current query when
  the timeout interval has been exceeded.
   
## See also

  [[\go]]
        ]]></Help>	
	</Property>
	
  	<Property bean="global" name="timer" property="visualTimerEnabled">
        <Description>Controls display of a visual query time</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  [[timer]] - Controls if a visual query timer is enabled

## Description
  The `${timer}` variable is a boolean variable used to control whether or 
  not jsqsh display a query timer clock while waiting for a query to complete.
  When enabled, the visual timer will appear for any query that takes longer
  than 5 seconds to complete.
   
## See also
  [[\go]]
        ]]></Help>	
	</Property>
	
  	<Property bean="global" name="exit_on" property="commandsToExitOnFailure">
        <Description>Cause a session to exit on command failure</Description>
        <Help><![CDATA[
## Variable

  `exit_on` - List of commands that, if they error, will exit the current session

## Description

  The `${exit_on}` variable may contain a comma delimited list of commands that,
  should the command return an error, will cause the invoking session to exit.
  The special name "any",
   
    \set exit_on=any
       
  will force the session to exit if any command returns an error. And the
  special name `none`,
   
    \set exit_on=none
       
  Indicates that no command (other than exit itself) should cause the session to
  exit.
   
  The typical use of exit_on would be to cause jsqsh to exit if a SQL statement
  returns an error which would usually be associated with the "go" command:
   
    \set exit_on=go
       
## Understanding errors

  JSqsh commands are very much like shell commands, each command 
  executed "exits" with an error code, with 0 indicating success and a non-zero 
  value indicating an error (the special `${rc}` variable can be used to see the 
  exit value of the most recently executed command).
   
  Most people using this variable will probably be interested in having 
  jsqsh exit only when invoking the `go` command because a failure probably 
  means the statement executed failed.  JSqsh has no specific understanding
  of what a specific JDBC driver may consider a failure--meaning it cannot
  classify one failure from another.  JSqsh simply deterines a failure if
  the JDBC driver throws an exception of any type (note that typically 
  database warnings or informational messages do now throw an exception).
   
## See also

  [[\go]]
        ]]></Help>	
	</Property>
	
</Variables>
