<Help>
	<Topic name="jsqsh">
		<Description>JSqsh command line options</Description>
		<HelpText><![CDATA[
## Synopsis

```
jsqsh [options] [connection-name]
   -A, --autoconnect          Allows jsqsh to automatically attempt to connect
   -C, --config-dir=dir       Configuration directory in addition to $HOME/.jsqsh.
   -D, --database=db          Database (catalog) context to use upon connection
   -b, --debug=class          Turn on debugging for a java class or package
   -w, --domain=domain        Windows domain to be used for authentication
   -d, --driver=driver        Name of jsqsh driver to be used for connection
   -R, --drivers=file         Specifies additional drivers.xml files to be loaded
   -e, --echo                 Echoes all input back. Useful for running scripts.
   -X, --exit=exit-type       Determines how exit status is computed ("total" failures or "last" failure
   -g, --gui                  Send all command output to a graphical window
   -h, --help                 Display help for command line usage
   -i, --input-file=file      Name of file to read as input. This option may be repeated
   -c, --jdbc-class=driver    JDBC driver class to utilize
   -u, --jdbc-url=url         JDBC url to use for connection
   -n, --non-interactive      Disables recording of input history, and line editing functionality
   -o, --output-file=file     Name of file send output instead of stdout
   -P, --password=pass        Password utilized for connection
   -p, --port=port            Listen port for the server to connect to
   -O, --prop=name=val        Set a driver connection property. Can be used more than once
   -r, --readline=method      Readline method (readline,editline,getline,jline,purejava)
   -S, --server=server        Name of the database server to connect to
   -z, --setup                Enters jsqsh connection setup wizard
   -s, --sid=SID              Instance id (e.g. Oracle SID) to utilize
   -t, --topic=topic          Displays detailed help on specific topics
   -U, --user=user            Username utilized for connection
   -v, --var=name=value       Sets a jsqsh variable. This option may be repeated
   -W, --width=cols           Sets the display width of output
```

## Description

JSqsh (pronounced "jay-skwish") is a command line tool primarily intended
for working with relational databases systems.  It provides all of the
basic functionality such as entering and executing queries, display results
in a variety of formats, as well as a number of advanced features, such
as command line editing, history recall, piping of output to other commands,
I/O redirection and much more. 

## Named connection setup

In the following sections, you will find a lot of options you may specify
to connect to a server (username, password, host, port, driver, etc.). To
avoid having to provide all of these options, jsqsh allow you to define a
named connection (or alias) for a set of connection properties and provides
a wizard for creating named connections.
   
### --setup (-S)

Starts jsqsh's connection setup wizard. This will take you through a series of 
steps to manage your named connections. One the connection wizard is complete 
you can use a named connection either by providing the connection name to 
jsqsh on startup:
       
    shell$ jsqsh mydb
          
or you can provide the name to the jsqsh `\connect` command at the jsqsh prompt:
       
    1> \connect mydb
   
## Connection options

The following options are all options available on the jsqsh command line
as well as to its `\connect` command, which may issue from the jsqsh prompt.
The presence of any of these options on the command line will cause jsqsh 
to automatically attempt to connect using the information provided, as 
if you had executed the `\connect` command.
   
In the help description below, you will see references to variables like
`${db}` or `${server}`. When an option says that it sets a given variable,
what is referring to is that if you look at a driver definition using the
command `\drivers`, like so:
   
    1> \drivers
    +-----------------+-------------+--------------------------------
    | Target          | Name        | URL                            
    +-----------------+-------------+--------------------------------
    | * MySQL         | mysql       | jdbc:mysql://${server}:${port} 
   
The option may set one of these variables. Not all variables are meaningful
or used by all drivers.
   
### --driver=*driver* (-d *driver*)

The name of the jsqsh driver definition that will be used for the connection 
(use `\drivers` to see a list).
              
### --server=*server* (-S *server*)

Sets the `${server}` variable, which typically specifies the server name to which 
you wish to connect.
                         
### --port=*port* (-p *port*)

Sets the `${port}` variable, which typically is the port on which the
server is listening on for connections. Note that if not provided, most
JDBC drivers defined within jsqsh will automatically select a default 
port that is suitable for a default installation of the server to which 
you are connecting.
                          
### --database=*db* (-D *db*)

Sets the ${db} property. This will cause the database context to be 
set to the provided database following connection to the server (in the 
JDBC world the database context is known as the "catalog"). 
Not all drivers support this behavior.
                          
### --username=*user* (-U *user*)

Sets the `${user}` property that determines the username that will be 
utilized to connect to the database.
                          
### --password=*pass* (-P *pass*)

Sets the `${password}` property that will be used to authenticate with 
the server.

### --sid=*SID* (-s *SID*)

Sets the `${SID}` property, and provides the Oracle SID that will be used 
when connecting to Oracle.

### --jdbc-url=*url* (-u *url*)

This option allows you to provide an explicit JDBC URL to utilize when 
establishing the connection rather than using jsqsh's driver mechanism. 
Typically use of this parameter also requires the use of the `--jdbc-class`
argument as well.
               
### --jdbc-class=*class* (-c *class*)

When utilizing a direct JDBC url (and not a jsqsh driver definition), this 
should be utilized to define which JDBC driver class will be utilized for 
the connection.
                          
### --domain=*domain* (-w *domain*)

For Windows based authentication, sets the `${domain}` property, specifying 
the windows domain to be utilized when establishing the connection. Not 
all JDBC drivers support this functionality.
                       
### --prop=*name=value* (-O *name=value*)

This option allows JDBC driver properties to be explicitly set prior to 
connecting, and may be listed more than once. For example:
                      
    \connect --prop compress=true --prop failover=false
                        
The set of properties that are available are specific to a given JDBC 
driver, so you'll need to consult the documentation for your driver for 
details.
                          
### connection-name 

If provided, this indicates the logical connection name that should be 
used to establish the connection. If additional arguments are provided, 
then they will override the same options associated with the logical 
connection name. See "\help connect" for details on named connections.

## General options

The following command line options are supported by jsqsh.
   
### --config-dir=*dir* (-C *dir*)

The `--config-dir` option can be used to specify a directory containing
jsqsh configuration files (see START UP, above). This directory will
be processed in addition (and following) `$HOME/.jsqsh`.  This option
may be provided more than once if you wish to read multiple configuration
directories.

### --debug=*class* (-b *class*)

Enable java debugging output for a specific jsqsh java class or package.
All such debugging messages will be issued to stdout of jsqsh
   
### --echo (-e)

Causes all input to be echoed to the screen. This is particularly useful
with the `--input-file` (`-i`) option, if you wish to see the supplied
input along with the output of the commands.

### --help (-h)

Display command line help information and exit.
   
### --input-file=*filename* (-i *filename*)

Indicates that input will be provided from an input file rather than
reading from interactive input from a user. 
       
This option may be provided more than once on the command line, and 
input will be read from all files that are provided in the order 
that they are provided. It is important to note that each input file 
is processed within the same physical jsqsh session. This means that 
configuration options or variables that are set by one input file can 
affect the following input file.
       
If the filename provided is `-` that indicates that the input should
be read interactively from the user (from "stdin"). This option is useful
if you wish to execute a "setup" script before supplying input, like so:
       
    jsqsh -i setup.sql -i -
    ...
    1> 
          
will read and execute the contents of setup.sql, then prompt the user
for interactive input.
       
### --non-interactive (-n)

When input is read from a file (`--input-file`), the input is automatically
considered non-interactive, and the following functionality is disabled:
       
* Display of the welcome banner
* Display of the prompt
* Recording of line editor line history 
* Recording of statement history
         
When input is read from stdin, however, jsqsh cannot detect if the 
input is actual user input or is redirected input from a file, like so:
       
    jsqsh < input.sql
           
so the `--non-interactive` flag may be used to force non-interactive behavior 
when it isn't desirable.
       
### --output-file=*filename* (-o *filename*)

Causes output to be redirected to an output file rather than the users
screen. Note that error output continues to go to the screen (stderr).
       
### --drivers=*file* (-R *file*)

The `--drivers` option can be used to explicitly load additional JDBC
driver definition files.  The driver definition file teaches jsqsh
how to load a given JDBC driver without the user having to provide
a full JDBC URL and driver class name.  Once jsqsh is started an 
example template for a driver definition file is placed in your
`$HOME/.jsqsh/drivers.xml`.  This option may be provided more than
once if you wish to load multiple driver definition files.

### --exit=*exit-value* (-X *exit-value*)

The `--exit` flag determines how jsqsh computes its final exit status. The
default is "total", in which the final exit code is the total number of
failures seen during the session.  A value of "last" indicates that the
the exit status should be that of the last executed command (an explicit
`\quit` command is excluded from consideration).

### --setup

Start's jsqsh directly into the driver/connection setup wizard.  This 
is the same as running the `\setup` command at the jsqsh prompt.

### --topic=*topic* (-t *topic*)

Displays the text of a builtin jsqsh help topic and then exits.  This
is the same as running the `\help` command. For example:

    jsqsh --topic help
    
will display help for the `\help`.

### --var=*name*=*value* (-v *name*=*value*)

The `--var` (`-v`) option may be used to explicitly set or define a 
jsqsh variable. For example, if you wish to enable variable expansion
during SQL execution you can do any one of the following:
          
    jsqsh --var expand=true
    jsqsh --var=expand=true
    jsqsh -vexpand=true
    jsqsh -v expand=true
    
This option may be provided more than once to set multiple variables.

### --width=*width* (-W *width*)

For certain display styles, such as `perfect` (see [[style]]), jsqsh will attempt to fit
the columns to the current display width.  The `--width` (`-W`) option allows
you to force the screen width to the specified value.

## Start up

Upon startup, jsqsh performs the following activities:
   
1. If `$HOME/.jsqsh` doesn't exist, it is created and populated with two
   files, `driver.xml` and `sqshrc`. These files are described below.
2. If `$HOME/.jsqsh/drivers.xml` file is present, it is loaded. This file 
   can be used to define JDBC drivers to jsqsh that it does not 
   understand natively. The default `drivers.xml` file is empty, but has 
   lots of comments and examples describing the format.
3. If `$HOME/.jsqsh/sqshrc` is read if present. This file main contain any
   jsqsh command or directive, and is typically used to set default
   configuration variables, classpath settings, aliases, etc.
4. If `$HOME/.jsqsh/history.xml` is present it is loaded. This file contains
   your previous query execution history (see [[\history]]).
5. Any additional configuration directories specified with `--config-dir` (`-C`)
   (see below) are processed in the same fashion as steps #2-#4.
6. Any additional driver definition files specified with `--drivers` (`-R`)
   (see below) are loaded.
7. If any connection options were provided (see **Connection options*, below)
   an attempt is made to connect with the driver. If this fails, jsqsh
   exits.
8. The jsqsh prompt is presented (in interactive mode) or input is processed
   if `--input-file` (`-i`) was provided.  

## See also

[[\connect]], [[\drivers]]
          ]]></HelpText>
</Topic>

	<Topic name="jni">
		<Description>Features provided by the jsqsh JNI layer</Description>
		<HelpText><![CDATA[
## Jsqsh JNI layer

JSqsh is written in almost 100% java code, making it very 
portable between platforms, however there are a few places 
where java just does not provide enough functionality to 
implement certain features that are needed by jsqsh, so jsqsh 
can optinally load  a shared library (or DLL) that provides
this additional  functionality. This shared library is
written using the Java Native Interface (JNI) and on UNIX
platforms is typically called 'libjsqsh.so' and on
Windows is 'libjsqsh.dll'.
            
The jsqsh shared library is not available on all platforms, and
jsqsh will generate a warning upon startup if it is unable to
load its JNI interface.  Lack of JNI causes the following
behavior:
            
* Operating system commands that are piped to (e.g. `go | grep ...`)
  will not have direct access to the console (in the UNIX world
  this is called "tty" access). This means that these commands 
  cannot perform any console operations. Specifically, commands
  such as "more" will not function properly because "more" needs
  to query the console as to its size and will be unable to do so.
          
* Similarly, the editor launched by `\buf-edit` will not have access
  to the console, so text-based editors such as `vi` or `emacs` 
  will not work properly. In this case, you will need to use a 
  graphical editor such as "notepad.exe" or "gvim".
		]]></HelpText>
</Topic>

<Topic name="welcome">
		<Description>The jsqsh welcome message</Description>
		<HelpText><![CDATA[
## Welcome to JSqsh!
            
It looks like this is the first time that you've run jsqsh (or
you just typed '\help welcome' at the jsqsh prompt). If this is
the first time you have run jsqsh, you will find that you have
a shiney new directory called '.jsqsh' in your home directory
and that this directory contains a couple of files that you
should be aware of:
            
* drivers.xml  
  JSqsh comes pre-defined to understand how to use
  a fixed number of JDBC drivers, however this file may be
  used to teach it how to recognize other JDBC drivers. The
  file is pretty well commented, so hopefully it is enough
  to get you started.
               
* sqshrc  
  Everything contained in this file is executed just
  as if you had typed commands at the sqsh prompt and is 
  the place where you can set variables and configure sqsh
  to your likings.
               
JSqsh is intended to be self-documenting. If you would like
to see this information again, then type '\help welcome' at 
the jsqsh prompt, or run '\help' to see a list of all help
topics that are available.
	  ]]></HelpText>
</Topic>

<Topic name="buffers">
    <Description>SQL buffers and how they are referenced.</Description>
    <HelpText><![CDATA[
## JSqsh SQL buffers
    
Each time you create and execute a SQL statement, that statement is saved
away into your SQL buffer history. The list of prior SQL statements 
can be displayed using the `\history` command.

Many jsqsh command allow you to refer to SQL buffers via special syntax,
each starting with an exclamation character (`!`).  This syntax allows for
the following forms:

* `!.`  
  Refers to the current SQL buffer that you are currently 
  typing in to (but have not yet executed).
     
* `!..`  
  Refers to the most recently executed SQL buffer.

* `!!`  
   A synonym for `!..`. In addition, typing `!!` at the prompt
   causes the current SQL buffer (`!.`) to be appended with the
   most recently executed SQL statement. This is a useful feature
   for re-executing the previous statment. For example, to re-execute
   the most recently executed SQL statement:
     
        1> !!
        ...
        5> \go
       
    The `!!` appends the previously executed statement to the current
    buffer (which was empty) and the \go, obviously, executes the
    statement.

* `!...`  
  Refers to the statement you executed two executions prior. Additional
  periods may be provided to continue moving back through executions 
  (e.g. `!.......` refers to the statement executed 6 executions prior).
     
* `!N`  
  This syntax allows you to refer to SQL statements executed a specific
  number of executions prior. For example `!0` refers to the current
  buffer (that has not yet been executed), `!1` refers to the 
  most recently execute statements, `!2` the one before that and so on.
     
## Examples

Examples of commands that utilize this syntax are `\buf-edit`, `\but-copy`,
and `\buf-append`.  For example:
    
    \buf-edit !!
       
indicates that the most recently executed statement should be edited.
	  ]]></HelpText>
</Topic>

<Topic name="license">
		<Description>Displays the jsqsh license</Description>
		<HelpText><![CDATA[
Copyright 2007-2015 Scott C. Gray and Others (see AUTHORS)
  
Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
You may obtain a copy of the License at
  
http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  
Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
limitations under the License.
	  ]]></HelpText>
</Topic>

<Topic name="contributors">
		<Description>Individuals who have contributed to jsqsh</Description>
		<HelpText><![CDATA[
## JSqsh contributors

The following individuals have contributed to the development of
jsqsh either by direct contribution of code, suggestions, or 
inspiration.
   
  * **Walter Jordan** (walter.gator at gmail.com) - Patches and useful suggestions.
  * **Ryan Stouffer** (rstouffer at gmail.com) - Enhancements and additions to GUI widgets.
  * **Scott Wakeling** (scott at diskfish.org) - Build enhancements for debian

	  ]]></HelpText>
</Topic>

<Topic name="options">
		<Description>Command line option processing</Description>
		<HelpText><![CDATA[
## Command line options

Jsqsh commands executed on the jsqsh command line follow many 
of the same rules as program executed at your computers command
line (well, unless you are used to working in the Windows 
command shell, then you'll find it is better).
   
All jsqsh commands accept command line options. These options
are provided in two different forms: a short form an a long form.
   
## Short options

Short command line options are provided in the form of a dash (`-`)
followed by a letter. For example, the `\connect` command requires
a username to be used to establish a connection to the database
server.  The short form of this option is `-U` followed by the name
of the user. You can either have a space following the username or 
not, so that:
   
    \connect -Usgray
      
is the same as:
   
    \connect -U sgray

In some cases, the command line option does not take an argument 
(in the above "sgray" was the argument to the `-U` option). For 
example, with the `\echo` command:
   
    \echo -n hello
      
the `-n` flag indicates that a new-line should NOT be displayed after 
printing the word "hello" 
   
## Long options

Short options are easy to enter, but for command, such as \connect,
which require a lot of options, it can begin to look like alphabet
soup:
   
    \connect -Usa -Pguessme -Dmaster -Ssql-prod -dmssql-jtds
   
To address this, every command line option also has an alternate
long form. For example, the equivalent of the `-U` option for 
`\connect` is (note the double-dashes, they indicate it is a long option):

    \connect --user=sgray
   
or
   
    \connect --user sgray
      
this, the full command line shown above would be:
   
    \connect --user=sa --password=guessme --database=master --server=sql-prod --driver=mssql-jtds
   
this form may take more typing but is much more explicit.
   
## Option documentation

In all help documents, options are generally shown as:
   
### --long-name1=*value* (-X *value*)
   
where the option `-X` is also known as `--long-name1` and takes
an argument (e.g. `-X value`, `-Xvalue`, `--long-name1=value`
or `--long-name1 value` are all the same).
   
### --long-name2\[=*value*\] (-Y [*value*])
      
where the option `-Y` is also known as `--long-name2` and has
a value that is not required. 
   
### --long-name3 (-Z)
    
where the option `-Z` is also known as `--long-name3` and does
not have an argument (e.g. `-Z`, or `--long-name3` are the same)
      
## Options supported by all commands

All jsqsh commands accept the following arguments:
   
### --gui (-g)

Display all output in a graphical popup window. This is useful for 
setting aside a result set for later reference while you continue to work.
               
### --help (-h)

Displays a description how to execute the command.
	  ]]></HelpText>
</Topic>

<Topic name="redirection">
		<Description>Command line output redirection</Description>
		<HelpText><![CDATA[
## Command line redirection

As with standard Bourne shell (and most other shells, for that 
matter), a command's output may be redirected using a special
notation interpreted by the jsqsh. The following may appear anywhere
on the command line, but only redirection that is specified prior
to a pipe (`|`) actually has any effect on the behavior of internal
jsqsh commands.
    
* `[n]>file`  

   Causes the output of the command to be redirected to a 
   file.  Following standard shell conventions, the `n` is 
   an optional number that can be used to indicate which
   output of the command is redirected to the file.  A `1`
   indicates the regular output should be redirected, and
   a `2` indicates only the errors should be redirected.
   If no number is provided, then regular output is diverted.
              
   For example:
              
        \go >tmp.out
   
   Sends the output of the `\go` command to a file called 
   `tmp.out`. Errors will still go to your screen.
                            
        \go 1>tmp.out
       
   Synonym for the above.
                            
        \go 2>tmp.out 
       
   The results from the `\go` will go to your screen but errors 
   will be captured in tmp.out.
    
* `[n]>>file`  

   This is identical to the above except that if the file 
   exists, it is appended to rather than overwritten.
    
* `[m]>&[n]`  

   This allows one type of output stream (regular output
   or errors) to be redirected to the other type of stream.
   For example:
              
        \go 2>&1

   Causes errors from the SQL to go to the regular output 
   stream
              
        \echo "Error!" 1>&2 

   Causes the output of the \echo command to be send to the error 
   stream.
                 
        \echo "Error!" >&2 

   A synonym for the above.
   
* `>+[id]`  

  This syntax is specific to jsqsh and is used to redirect the output 
  from the current command to the context of another session (specified 
  by `id`). If no session id is provided, then the output of the current 
  session is "looped back" to itself. See **Session redirection**, below 
  for details.
             
## Pipes and redirection

It is important to understand that jsqsh handles pipes very differently
from that of a typical shell. In jsqsh anything following a pipe 
character (`|`) is passed directly to the operating system shell, which
means that any I/O redirection following the pipe character is being
performed by your local operating system shell and not by jsqsh and will
therefore follow whatever rules are defined by your O/S shell.

## Session redirection

Session redirection is indicated by the special syntax `>+[id]` where
`id` is the id of the session that you wish to re-direct the output to.
If the id is not specified then the output is sent back to your current
session for subsequent processing.
    
When jsqsh encounters a session redirection the following takes place:
    
1. A temporary file is created and the commands output is sent to
   that file.
2. If the command involves a pipe, the output of the pipe is sent to
   that file.
3. After the command completes, the contents of the file is executed
   in the context of the target session as if:
       
        \eval tmp_file
       
   was executed in the target session.
       
The important item to note is that any output from the command being
directed is treated *exactly* as if the user had typed it into the
prompt in the context of the target session.
    
Here's why this is so important to understand:
    
    1> echo 'select 1' >+2 
       
will *not* cause a `select 1` to be executed in session #2. All that
will happen is that jsqsh will switch to the context of session #2,
pretend that the user has typed `select 1`, and then switch back to the
current session.  The end result, is that a `select 1` will be appended
to the current SQL buffer (the SQL buffer is independant of sessions).
    
If you actually want to execute the command then you can do one of two
things:
    
    1> echo 'select 1;' >+ 2
       
or 
    
    1> echo 'select 1' >+2
    2> \echo 'go' >+2
       
In the first case, the semicolon causes the execution of the SQL
and in the second, the `go` executed in the context of session #2
causes the execution.
	  ]]></HelpText>
</Topic>

<Topic name="editing">
        <Description>JSqsh line editing</Description>
        <HelpText><![CDATA[
## JSqsh line editing

Jsqsh can utilize several different line editing libraries that allow
you to move around and edit the current line you are typing at, as well
as to scroll backwards and forwards through previous lines of text
that you have typed in.  Note that this is different from recalling
and editing entire statements: for that, please see the `\help` for 
[[buffers]], [[\history]], and [[\buf-edit|\buf_edit]].

## Choosing a line editor

JSqsh uses JLine as the default line editor (see below).  However,
it supports a number of editors, You can control which editor is used 
via either the `--readline` command line option when starting jsqsh, 
or the `JSQSH_READLINE` environment variable, so to one of the values 
below:

Value     | Description
----------|-------------------------------------------
jline     | JLine (built-in)
readline  | GNU Readline (via java-readline, see below)
editline  | BSD Editline (via java-readline, see below)
getline   | Getline (via java-readline, see below)
none      | None (no line editor)

## Jline line editing

As of JSqsh 1.5, the default line editor is JLine:

https://github.com/jline/jline2

This library provides full line editing, history recall, searching,
emacs and vi keymaps, configurable keymaps and a bunch of other 
functionality.  The JLine library is not 100% java and relies upon
some native code.  As a result, it is only supported on Windows (32
and 64 bit), Linux (32 and 64 bit) and MacOS.

## GNU readline support

GNU readline used to be the default editor in JSqsh, however as of
JSqsh 1.5, JLine is now the default and readline is not included
with the JSqsh distribution. This was due to both the JSqsh license 
change to the Apache license, as well as to the fact that the 
Java-Readline library appears to be abandoned. 

While Jsqsh retains its support for Java-Readline, the library
is not included with the jsqsh distribution.  If you wish to utilize
the library, most Linux distributions can easily install
Java-Readline using the software package manager (typically under
a package named "libreadline-java").

## Java-readline detection
   
The JSqsh startup script will automaticallyl detect and utilize
java-readline if it is installed on your system on a debian based
linux distribution (e.g. Debian, Ubuntu, Mint, etc.).  If these are found, 
then readline support will be enabled. 
      ]]></HelpText>
</Topic>

<Topic name="storedprocs">
        <Description>Calling stored procedures with JSqsh</Description>
        <HelpText><![CDATA[
# Calling stored procedures

JSqsh provides special support for calling stored procedures that require
output (OUT) or input/output (INOUT) parameters. 
   
## JDBC escape syntax
   
The JDBC standard defines a canonical way of executing stored procedures 
in a manner that abstracts away the specifics of how procedures are invoked
for a given platform.  The following example executes a procedure passing one
input argument and retrieving one output argument using this syntax:
   
    1> { call my_test_proc(10, ?) };
    +-------------+
    | Param #1    |
    +-------------+
    | Fred        |
    +-------------+
      
here, a question mark (`?`) is used to denote an output parameter. After
execution, the contents of that output parameter is displayed as shown.
   
In addition, many platforms allow you to also get a return value from the
stored procedure.  To do this in JDBC escape syntax do:
   
    1> { ?= call my_test_proc(10, ?) };
    +-------------+-------------+
    | Return Code | Param #2    |
    +-------------+-------------+
    |           0 | Fred        |
    +-------------+-------------+
      
In the case of input/output parameters, jsqsh slightly extends the JDBC
standard with `?=<value>` which indicates that the parameter is an INOUT
parameter, and that the initial input value should be `<value>`, like so:
   
    1> { ?= call double_my_inout_param_value(10, ?=321) };
    +-------------+-------------+
    | Return Code | Param #2    |
    +-------------+-------------+
    |           0 | 642         |
    +-------------+-------------+

## Automatic "CALL" handling

The JDBC escape syntax above is awkward to work with, so jsqsh will attempt
to automatically recognize when you are trying to call a procedure.  It does
so according to the following rules:
   
  1. The first keyword in your statement is `CALL`
  2. There are one or more parameter markers (`?`) following the CALL keyword
     (`?` characters contained in comments or string constants are ignored)
  
If both of these are true, then jsqsh automatically takes your statement
and attempts to make it a JDBC escape syntax statement.  For example, 
executing the following:
   
    1> call my_proc(10, ?);
   
will cause jsqsh to turn it into:
   
    { ?= call my_proc(10, ?) }
   
and execute the statement.   

## Output cursors

Unfortunately, there is no standard in JDBC for the handling of CURSOR 
output parameter types, so each JDBC driver deals with them differently.
As a result, jsqsh currently only has an understanding of how to handle
CURSOR output parameters for IBM DB2 and Informix, and Oracle.  
   
When faced with an OUTPUT parameter of type cursor, jsqsh will display
the results like so:
   
    1> call my_cursor_output(?);
      
    Parameter #2 CURSOR:
    +---+
    | 1 |
    +---+
    | 5 |
    +---+

    +-------------+
    | Return Code |
    +-------------+
    |           0 |
    +-------------+
      ]]></HelpText>
</Topic>

</Help>
